so now let's look at how do we form the
offset index and tag in the address for
set associative caches this is a two-way
set associative cache that has four sets
when the processor produces an address
the least significant bits that tell us
where in the block we are are still
determined by the block size the index
bits are the ones that tell us which set
are we talking about so the number of
index bits is determined by how many
sets we have in this case we have four
sets so we need two index bits the
remaining bits are the Tag like in a
direct map cache once we have placed a
line in for example set zero we know
that everything that maps to set zero
will have bits 0 0 here so we don't have
to keep that in the tag in set zero we
only need to make sure that what we now
need matches what we have in the
uppermost bits not in the index bits
because the fact that we are looking at
set zero means that we have already
determined that these bits are 0 0 and
everything that we could have placed
here also has z0 bits in the index
interestingly a direct map cache of the
same size would have one more index bit
so it would have slightly smaller tag